So next up we have Don.
who now works at GitHub Next.
Get sorry
man. Moved on from.
Imagine I just did a strike through.
I'm so used to markdown I just strike through my head.
And inventor of f sharp and so many other things.
Let's just shut up and get over to Don, okay? Don.
Round of applause, please.
Thank you.
It is. What a wonderful conference, man.
I haven't been at a conference where I just want to go and watch every talk
I missed.
And like, I'm thinking, which session will I go in?
These are all interesting.
Is so much going on at the moment.
And of course, is matching what's kind of going on in the industry.
We all know it's it's a time of huge change,
excitement, concerns, you know,
and, and a lot of ideas are kind of information.
Information.
And I work at a wonderful place called GitHub.
Next we are a team.
You can kind of think of us I guess a key difference.
We're not like a research team in the sense we like publish
kind of peer reviewed papers, but we do get to decide what we work on.
The management, trust us, sort of to set our direction.
And over the last year
we've been we've been taking advantage of that to really set a direction,
I think, for the industry to set a direction for GitHub.
And I'm really happy, really proud of what we've been doing over the last year.
I want to talk a bit about it.
So yeah, our job, our mandate.
Yeah, very broad future of software development.
We all know that it's all about AI.
Some of the people who started
the original OG GitHub copilot completions
kind of kicked everything off back in 20 2122.
They formed GitHub next.
So we inherit the spirit of those people who were working on on copilot.
Completions are okay. Yes.
Times images to use.
I use the wizard image a lot. I,
I used to work on programing languages.
It was really exciting, really amazing, amazing things to work on.
But what I tell people now is I was working on shovels,
you know, making shovels.
We were all obsessed about shovels.
If you want to watch something sort of British about shovels,
go look up Ripping Yarns and The Tale of Eric White.
He is obsessed about shovels, and we were a bit like that.
It's amazing.
Those are incredibly powerful machines, programing languages.
They they're good construction material.
We wanted C sharp, F sharp, strong typing, Java, all of it.
We were really good construction materials,
but we have to be honest, today people are kind of moved on from shovels.
They want magic wand and they've got magic ones.
You've all got magic wands in your hands that make the shovels dance, that
make the machines dance and make the tools and the construction materials.
You know, you can boom.
And this is incredible. It's disturbing.
I mean, it's disturbing to sit in a meeting where you've got, like.
I mean, it's like the Council of Wizards in Lord of the rings, right?
Everybody sitting around, you know that at the end of the meeting,
any single wizard can walk out of there and go, boom!
Kind of.
By the end of the day, they've magic up whatever you're kind of talking about.
But how do you manage like a group of wizards?
Right.
That's some people have been talking about that kind of problem.
And it it's a big problem.
It's just a big kind of change.
So I, I use this slide
with undergraduates as well here at King's College in London. And
you know, we
have to get across to the next generation that they have these incredible powers.
And they learn to
need to learn to channel them, and they need to be positive about it.
But we need to understand that there's
a lot of responsibility that comes with these powers as well.
They can blow up in your face.
I don't particularly Rings of Power, but here's
a young Gandalf arriving in middle earth blowing himself up.
There's lots of Harry Potter examples to of wizards
kind of blowing themselves up and useful to communicate
the kind of risks and dangers of kind of channeling the power incorrectly.
And that image I love images,
you know, the channeling that'll come back in the rest of the talk.
Now I want to talk about a change which in images.
Okay.
And it's a change, in a way, from the image of copilot to the image of
continuous AI.
And the image of copilot is you've got you of the individual.
It's about individual productivity.
And that's incredibly important.
Most of your experiencing kind of individual productivity
tools, your coding agent environments or developer
environments equipped with agent chats, your chats equipped
with developer capabilities and individual productivity is an immensely
important part of the industry, and everybody is kind of piling in
to kind of make individuals are more productive.
But in the history of software development tools, there's always been
these two different polarities, kind of two different coalescing points.
And one is about individual productivity.
And you see that in the development environment.
And that's had a long, long history.
And then there's been this other polarity which is about the SDLC,
which is about automation,
which is about the continual kind of processes that need to go on.
It's about teams, it's about collaboration.
And I think the industry in there,
right, rightful pursuit of individual productivity
has maybe not been focusing on automation
and not been focusing on continuity.
And at the heart of GitHub is, of course, continuity.
And so we went back a year ago and we kind of did a conceptual project.
It's almost like a linguistic project in a way to say,
let's take the ethos
of continuous integration and continuous
deployment, and let's say, actually we were missing something all along.
There's a third pillar to that.
There's actually three.
It's not CI, CD, it's ci, CD
and continuous ai ci. And
we in a way what do we mean by that.
Well let's start to give that some some, some.
If we're going to introduce a term like that we have to give it some meaning.
Give it some body.
And when did you start unpicking it.
The examples are absolutely everywhere.
And there are lots of people in the industry doing continuous AI,
making offerings about automated uses
of AI in our development processes.
And you see people coming up with flows.
Some of them are automated,
some of them are semi-automated about continuous documentation.
And then when you start to think about it, it begins to have
a different feel to individual productivity, a different emphasis.
The problem with piling everything into individual productivity is that all these
kind of conflicting kind of goals that the individual is under,
they have to be productive, but they also have to be quality.
They have to, they have to.
They've got to flow.
They have to serve the work queue
coming in, but they also have to work on one particular item.
And so the individual becomes a bit of a kind of crunch point
for all the information flows going through a software project. And
when you start to
think of things in continuous terms, you can start to unpick that a bit
and you can talk about things like, actually,
I would like to have continuous code improvement in my repository.
And, and, and it's actually real.
And if you want to get a feeling for what my kind of day is like
is on my blog, you know, here's a typical morning.
I wake up to code improvements, start my day with code that's better provided
by my continuous improvement processes so we can unpick quality.
We can unpick that kind of logjam.
And to say here, actually lying in bed,
I can check the pull requests that have been created for me.
And yeah, start my day with code better.
It's a wonderful, incredible way to start the day as an engineer
by having a set of improvements delivered right into your repository.
Okay, so continuous continuous code improvement,
dealing with the incoming continuous triage, continuous fault analysis.
Now that's a big, big one.
And if you saw May's talk from the startup called Hud
at this conference, I'll be showing one slide from her talk later.
She's using a generic workflows and continuous quality
continuous fault analysis in really incredible ways.
And things like continuous accessibility to say, actually,
I don't really know how to do accessibility.
Well, I can't actually afford to hire an accessibility engineer,
but I can actually get the agents to be taking it, to be
doing the walkthroughs of the running application in C in my continuous system,
and actually checking out whether we've got some basics of
in place, and of course,
getting the experts when we actually are able to as well.
So continuous AI so these are automated
there, repetitive, collaborative, integrated, auditable
and crucially there are lots and lots of variants of these things.
And then you think to yourself, what does this feel like.
And it feels like ci CD.
So continuous AI is a question to the industry
about how we think about AI, how we think about AI automation.
But it's also a question to GitHub, because GitHub is a wonderful place
and all the other platforms that provide CI, CD, because in a way it's
a question where if ci CD is the answer to certain kinds of automation,
then those platforms should also be
the answer to AI automation as well.
There can be win win between these platforms.
They can include a mix of algorithmic or
traditional computational flows and flows.
And we use those kind of things all the time.
And of course, they're event triggered, they're proactive,
and it's about collaboration, team productivity,
not just individual productivity.
Okay, so continuous AI, but of course, if we're posing
a question to the industry and to GitHub, then we need an implementation of that.
And we have a wonderful implementation.
You'll see many implementations of continuous AI and variations on it.
But our implementation is called GitHub workflows.
You can use it today. It's all open source.
It is in a way additive to GitHub.
It's very closely aligned to GitHub actions.
And effectively it takes a specification
of a agentic workflow and hardens it into a GitHub action.
I don't mean compile it,
I mean it's got a prompt and it wraps that so that it's running in.
It's mainly about hardening it in a security sense
to make sure you can trust the flow that's being implemented by that workflow.
So let's take a look at GitHub Agentic Workflows.
You can use it today I will the I'll just call out the key.
You know it's this line repository automation.
That's again another bit of terminology which is an immensely powerful thing
turning every repository into a software factory
just like CI, CD automated
automated your build and deployments so we can automate
a huge range of subjective activities in the repository.
How do we do it?
Repository automation, running the coding agents you know and love.
So you're running Claude or you're running copilot
CLI Claude code or copilot CLI or Gemini CLI
or Codex are ultimately being hosted inside GitHub actions.
And the end result is that you're running the coding agents
you know and love with strong guardrails in a platform,
your company or you are probably already using a GitHub.
Actions is has this amazing quality.
And it's it's that when a company adopts GitHub actions,
what they're actually doing is giving a playground an automation
playground where developers can claim, can make
and use cloud resources, that is compute, network and storage,
and AI and and llms
or coding agents in the in their context, in their working context.
And it's like equipping every developer with the ability
to make multiple factories in their working context.
That is a hugely empowering and democratizing thing.
And it's a big part of why GitHub actions are successful.
You don't have to go and ask them.
Maybe there may be rules you have to follow in your organization,
but generally you don't have to go
and ask the kind of the cloud people for more cloud resources.
You just claim them through GitHub actions.
So it's an empowering platform,
and we're bringing a agentic automation right into that platform.
Okay.
So yeah that's summarizing what I just said.
Right. Let's take a look at an example.
Dead simple front matter plus markdown.
You check it in you harden it to a YAML.
It runs. That's it.
You have a factory one file checked in one file.
Plus it's hardening, checked in.
So it's got some triggers at the top.
It's very familiar to people who do actions.
This is going to run every week.
It's got okay.
It's got a safe output specification.
So these coding agents when they run every week in GitHub actions
you're going to be asleep right. It's going to be the middle of the night.
You're suddenly running a coding engine in the middle of your repository.
Like what the heck, right? How is that safe?
And it's safe.
They run read only with no access to secret, no direct access to secrets.
They run in a container and they have an extremely narrow output channel.
In this case, it's allowed to create one issue.
That's all.
This figure does a hand off of its output.
It's a bit like a plan apply kind of thing, and the apply is not done it.
It's not done through MCP.
It's done as a secondary stage.
And they're actually threat detection and put in between those stages.
So safe outputs with narrow channels, not just arbitrary permissions
to write to your issues or write to the contents of your repository.
It's got some tools of some kind and it's got some,
some prompting or sort of natural language programing usually very
sort of
deliberately ambiguous, genuinely useful ambiguity.
And it's kind of actions familiar to those.
Nearly everyone uses GitHub actions in some way or another,
and it assumes we're running on the GitHub what I call the GitHub
information fabric, or the GitHub data model.
That means it's you can have safe outputs to create issues.
You can have various tools to kind of read various kinds of inputs.
You can do cross repository ones with the right permissions set up,
so you can begin to have agentic workflows
that run across multiple repositories or indeed over your entire organization.
If the permissions are given
okay and they usually are, there can be data collection steps.
You can have traditional actions jobs in the front matter.
And then in some way they produce some sort of outputs on GitHub.
Pull requests or issues.
They don't ever merge pull requests.
The pull request is a kind of hard point that it's always the human
in the loop through a pull request.
Okay, so there's just another example.
If you triage with a different set of triggers at the top
that every time miniature is opened or reopened, it's going to do
some kind of issue triage on this, on this, on this thing.
And it is dead simple.
To get started, just install the extension, which is the hardener,
the sort of compiler if you like, but it's really about hardening the workflow
and run through an ad wizard on a typical on a typical workflow.
And bang,
you're doing a generic automation, getting pull requests or issue
analysis and many, many other applications delivered into your repository.
Okay,
so safety I've kind of
touched on the main things about safety, but it's absolutely crucial
if you're going to automate to take safety seriously.
And if anybody is talking about automation and not talking about safety,
it's like, you know, ask questions, right?
Ask the right questions.
Because this
unlike individual productivity,
there's a conflict between safety and productivity.
And we all know this.
The technicians can come up with things to make your coding agent sessions safer
and sort of lock them down and tell them you're only allowed to use certain MCP.
You've got to approve every single tool call and the individual just says, no,
you know, just turn it all off like we all do it.
Just like, you know, we don't care. We just want.
We just want the coding. We just want the productivity.
Give me more productivity in automation.
It's actually the opposite way around.
It's like a rail track.
The better the quality of the rails that you're on, the faster your train can go,
the more you can automate, the more confidence
you can have to build automation flows or factories
or whatever you want to call them, which operates safely
and within the intended bounds and the intended channels. So
in automation,
think check carefully
that you are getting a security architecture.
Do not run coding agents directly in GitHub actions or any other CI
CD thing without a security architecture of some kind.
You must always have a security architecture as you should
and as you should for all your automation, but it's absolutely crucial
in the context of a working and a agentic automation.
So execution and sandbox permissions are minimize
the agentic set runs read only no secrets and very narrow safe outputs.
That means there's often a preload step where the an algorithmic step
gets lots of information, maybe CI logs or whatever the agentic step
is going to work on gets a big package of information ready for the
for the coding agent to kind of run over in its kind of safe, sandboxed way.
And then you have this narrow output to this intended channel
where the blast radius is extremely reduced.
Maybe create one issue or create one pull request.
And it's got these checks for threat detection,
and you have human oversight guaranteed through the issue and the pull request.
And we turn off things like shared package coaches
to make sure we don't get package cache poisoning and other things going on.
And all the outgoing network is firewalls and and controlled.
Okay.
So once you have continuous AI and once you have as a sort of a
as a philosophy and a agentic workflows as an implementation,
there's several directions.
And this is really where I think the whole industry is going
is several directions you can go in.
One of them is the Agent Zoo, and this is where you or are
or the agent factory.
And we we put together.
This is the approach adopted by Pelli on my team, who is a wonderful collaborator.
I don't think you might call him kind of crazy, because he has taken
the philosophy of let's create a new antic,
automated the agentic workflow for just about everything, and it's created
hundreds and hundreds of these things for different kinds of working.
And we were so taken by his work that we wrote it up in this kind of agent
factory.
And, and you can kind of start to see what he's using these things for.
And we built GitHub workflows using this technique,
and we built a blog series called Meet the Workflow.
So please check that out.
And there's some really interesting themes come out.
This idea of continuously simplifying your code and making your code
better, continuously refactoring your code like a thing
to take large files and split them apart into a really.
And actually the code ends up really, really nice to apply styling to
your code.
These very subjective decisions that agents can make could be.
And there's other aspects of improvement and documentation that we kind of
bring out in this blog series.
If you click through on some of these things, you'll actually see
very direct examples of how these things actually,
you know, in this use of semantic function refactoring, the workflow had 112 merged
PRS out of 142, and we follow the causal chains of those.
This is such and such an issue analyzed.
The code organization opportunities led to a certain
pull request that led to a certain kind of outcome.
So please take a look through that.
Now, having an agent zoo, that's actually not my style.
I don't do that.
I actually focus on a single workflow that does many things.
And so I've put those together in a set of samples.
One of them is for continuous test improvement.
Another one is continuous performance engineering on your code base.
For the one I really want to talk about is one that's very close to my heart.
As an open source maintainer, I maintain about seven
open source repositories, and I.
I really care for the open source maintainers in the world.
They're under huge amount of pressure at the moment.
You know, if these if these repositories have, say, 200 or 400 open issues
and each of those are going to take a day, a night of
of kind of spare time work to kind of work through.
That's a lot of time you're asking of open source maintainers.
And what happens is these repositories end up dormant.
They end up kind of not with no forward velocity at all.
I still want them maintained, but they but you know, they're kind of stuck there
logjam there. They're not progressing.
So let's take a look at our repository maintenance
I will talk about repo assist.
Now repo is one particular agent workflow.
And I just want to dig in here to what it does okay.
It's pretty simple.
It reads it's memory.
And then it chooses a couple of a smorgasbord of tasks.
And of course this is under your control as a repository, as a maintainer
you can shape these tasks.
You can delete them off, you can add new tasks.
And just once a day or some appropriate kind of cadence, it's going to wake up
and it's going to do these things in the repository.
And there was talk about like repository maintainer holidays
yesterday in Jack Jack talk from Google.
You can actually enable this kind of thing while you're away on your holiday
limiting the task.
Maybe it will reply hey, I'm away on holiday, but the AI says such
and such about this kind of about this kind of issue
that you're kind of talking about, or you can just use it as a general
kind of background assistant to help you work in the repository.
The triage, propose improvements, update, manage labels, you know,
whatever you choose as a set of tasks.
And that's what I was using in this
in this work here to start your day with code.
That's better.
So repo assist try and guess where I started to use
repo assist in this repository.
This is the number of open issues.
And this was back in March.
And this is a repository that I maintain one called
maintained one called FSharp.Data.
And it was basically a dormant repository.
You can see that there was there was nothing happening,
but there was a big fat issue backlog that nobody was ever going to look at.
Turn on repo assist.
And I actually started to be joy being a maintainer again.
We ended up doing three major releases that went over the entire issue backlog.
Some of them were problems, some of them were feature requests.
And bang!
It was so much fun to suddenly work on these things.
The AI would be commenting on the issue with a very good and accurate
assessment of an issue from even back into the 2018,
or there were still issues around which they were valuable,
and it's a form of data mining.
We're turning we're turning backlog into forward progress.
We're turning dormancy into forward velocity as another one.
Deedle, another library that was pretty much dormant.
Here's a whole set of these.
Not all of these are maintained by me.
So there are other maintainers picking up the particular repo assist
workflow, customizing it for their own needs, and you kind of see
the range of different outcomes of kind of this is on issues in the repository.
Now some of these repositories also had incoming.
Some of them kind of had had were more dormant.
And so you see a range of different outcomes.
And we've written a report which you're very welcome to, to read is called
the Impact of Automated Repository Maintenance Assistance.
Big thank you to the maintainers who worked with me on this and that.
Other people get up next.
And you can kind of see the changes in velocity in those repositories.
Not all of them, but most and most of them achieve forward velocity.
You can see the graphs on that.
And all of this is leading to a different kind of thinking, where
suddenly you can begin to use factory thinking.
You can start to use process flow models.
You can start to think about this, about what is actually going on
in these repositories as we start to automate what is happening.
So the repository as an automated software factory,
we have of course, already been automated factories
through continuous integration and deployment, but we're adding
a whole new range of kind of machines that can work on the production
line of issues and pull requests and other kind of activity
that's happening in the repository.
You could create sub factories.
You don't have to turn the whole whole repository.
You can kind of carve out parts of work through labeling or issue titles
and other ways of, of working.
And we've written that some of this up
as a blog: repository as a human-agent knowledge factory.
And when I think of a repository now, this is what I think of.
It's a site where humans and agents come together to work collaboratively
to get forward velocity through our through the through for the team
and for the for the for the production process that's happening.
Okay.
So some kind of factory flow, once you start having
a flow based thinking, everything becomes about flow.
You kind of look at these different repositories.
You can say some of them are blocked and they blocked
well, some of them are flowing and some of them are kind of idle.
There's actually no more input coming into those systems.
And they're actually when we say blocked, they're actually kind
of gated on human requirements.
And that's okay.
It's always okay to slow down the factory.
You know, if you've got a little factory
running at home, you don't want it running all night.
Right? Maybe waking up in the middle of your sleep or something like that.
You might you can gate the factory on human and organizational needs.
And it's so, so.
And that is totally okay.
Humans are absolutely part of this process.
And the human needs are paramount throughout what we're building.
But you as a repository owner are probably now
going to be a factory or a flow designer.
And if you if your aim is productivity
through the taking into account the human concerns,
if your aim is productivity, then you have to get production
flowing at high quality and the right cost.
And so we're going to see a lot more process engineering kind of thinking,
you know, go read books and the kind of chemical industry
or the or the mechanical engineering kind of industry or the or all the other
kind of engineering disciplines, which are all about this kind of thinking.
And we now have to take that kind of thinking and bring it
into the software development process.
So things jam up.
Of course they do.
And I think what a lot of people are experiencing at the moment is
they're working in the middle of a big logjam,
and they unclear part of it and say, oh my God, look at these agents.
I've got to set up this thing.
And and then it jams on another part of the flow, you know,
because somebody else, it hands off to somebody else
who doesn't actually do anything with that kind of work.
So getting ourselves from the kind of logjam state that a lot of enterprises
are in into a kind of flowing state, there's a lot of work
that needs to be do to to
modern enterprise software development.
So our I just wanted to call out
one other big application of this kind of thinking. And
I'm in.
May's work with HUD is just amazing because she's
she's using GitHub Agentic Workflows, and she's using it to do a weekly report.
Now, people usually look at that weekly report sample and say,
do I really want a report every week on my repository?
Maybe not just a generic research report, but what about if you're getting a
report that from a set of probes into your production system,
which are analyzing all your faults and problems,
all your request failures in
and bringing that up each week
into your surfacing that information into your team.
So it's part of it is about the quality of the data,
the quality of the probes, the quality of the kind of observation
you have of the factory and the quality that's being being produced.
And then surfacing that up into
in to you, into your team.
And as, as May says, the performance sprint, you run normally,
you run it every few months and suddenly you can run it every week.
Okay.
So the repository is an automated software factory.
I'm doing this like this morning I was working on two sub
factories to do with, with with parts of GitHub.
One of them is a factory to deal with. One problem.
So we have some some algorithmic things that look over our database
requests from production and from CI.
And we find the one problems, we catalog them all
and then we start to try and get a factory flowing.
Now my factory is not flowing at the moment.
It's like we haven't got a sufficient quality gate.
We're not checking, you know, and we know that.
And instead of going and fixing up the issues and saying, okay,
we can fix this one up manually, the key thing, step step is to step back and say,
let's add a quality gate to the factory so we can get the whole factory flowing.
Because we've got hundreds of these N plus ones we have to work through.
CI improvements is another factor I'm working on to reduce CI times.
And again, part of the factory is the quality gates that I need to add
to the to the to the factory.
So just to wrap up are
part of this is about what is work going to be like in the future.
And to me it's crucial to remember that
it's not about it's not about like
work is not a fixed there's not a fixed amount of work to be done.
There's a huge amount of work that needed to be done
that was that was simply not being done because it was labor constrained
and too expensive.
So the maze example is a good one.
How often do we do those performance or quality sprints?
Well, not often enough.
Right now. We can do them every week, right?
We can automate that whole process.
So the A and so there's work that was being done can now be done.
The car the automobile led to travel that wasn't being done before.
The factory led to millions of quality products that weren't being done before.
Medicine led to diseases being treated that weren't being treated before.
So more overall work is getting getting done, more output,
more productivity at high, I believe we can AI can now be a new
a totally see change in quality in the software industry.
If we think about it the right way and we we,
we think about what process is aiming towards quality
and not just towards slop and other outcomes.
Okay, so that's all new work, new futures and GitHub workflows.
Use it today and we'd love to have your feedback.
And it is in technical preview and we'll be going to public preview soon.
So thank you very much. Massive round of applause.
Don't sign. Thank you so much.
Stay right where you are.
Next speaker is coming up